and welcome back in today's video we'll
be talking about mortgage insurance
premiums or MIP and how that relates to
FHA Loans so let's get started so let's
talk about what is FHA so FHA stands for
federal housing Administration so the
FHA was created in 1934 and it is
another sub-agency within the U.S
Department of Housing and Urban
Development otherwise known as HUD so
now the FHA in order to provide housing
for Americans does this thing where it
provides mortgage insurance to specific
lenders in order for lenders to accept
people who are less than perfect credit
scores and have a lower amount for a
down payment the idea is that these
mortgages which are backed by the
government allow for lenders to be more
flexible which then allows more
Americans to have homes how does the FHA
mortgage insurance work so like I
mentioned before the purpose of having
FHA mortgage insurance provide on FHA
backed loans is the fact that it
protects the lender again mortgage
insurance in this case does not protect
the borrower it protects the lender so
how it works is that if the borrower
default on a loan which means that they
do not pay for it then when the house
goes for or closed if there is a loss
towards the lender side and the home
sold for less than what the original
loan Mount was for then the lender can
file a claim with the FHA to make some
of that money back again remember that
the mortgage insurance does not protect
the borrower it is for the lender how is
FHA mortgage insurance paid well there's
actually two types of FHA mortgage
insurance so let's cover the first type
the first type is The Upfront mortgage
insurance premium otherwise known as the
ufmip is a one-time payment and made at
the closing of the home now the ufmip
can be paid in cash or it could be
included in the finance charges
generally the UF MIP is required in
almost all FHA backed loans however
there are some exceptions please see
your Loan mortgage originator for
additional clarifications for your
specific circumstances essentially just
note that if you are financing the your
UF MIP then you are also paying for it
with interest because it is rolled into
your entirety of the loan it's also
important to note that the UF MIP is not
refundable even if you sell the house or
pay off the loan so how is the UF MIP
calculated well there's a couple of
factors that are tied to how much this
initial premium is going to be the first
is what's your total loan amount the
second is how long of a term is that
loan and the third one is what is your
loan to value ratio otherwise known as
LTV so the LT TV ratio broken down is
your loan divided by the appraised value
of the house the higher the loan to
value the higher the um FIP can be two
the second part of FHA mortgage
insurance is what is usually called the
MIP which is the annual mortgage
insurance premium and this is what gets
paid on a monthly basis so let's break
it down so when you have an FHA loan
every year of that loan you will have a
mortgage insurance premium but although
it's an annual mortgage insurance
premium they break it down to you in
monthly installments and tie it to your
mortgage payment like the ufmip the same
three factors affect what is your MIP so
again it's your loan to value ratio the
loan amount and then your term how is
FHA mortgage insurance different than
private mortgage insurance well with one
one is applicable to FHA loans and one
isn't FHA mortgage insurance is
applicable to loans that are from FHA
private mortgage insurance is usually
tied to Conventional loans which if you
need to know and more information about
PMI check out this video also there's a
difference in the removal across the two
in FHA Loans if you paid for your house
with a down payment of less than 10
percent after 2013 you will actually
have to have your MIP for the entirety
of the loan unlike PMI which
automatically gets removed once you have
22 percent of equity in the house that
is not the case for FHA another
difference is that if you did pay more
than 10 percent as a down payment for an
FHA loan then your MIP will be at least
mandatory in most cases for a minimum of
11 years out of your mortgage term and
again it can vary dependent on the
particular terms so make sure you you
talk to your lender about that alright
so that's the general basics in regards
to an FHA mortgage insurance if you have
any questions please leave a comment
below do me a favor give this video a
like make sure you are subscribed if you
aren't subscribed already and if you
could share it with somebody who might
also need this information as always
here and happy to help if you do have a
question that I don't know how to answer
I'll let you know I don't know the
answer try to find the answer and then
let you know how it came up with said
answer so that way in the future you
know how to go and look for the answers
yourself
and as always I hope you have a great
one and I'll see you in the next video
bye